[Music]
the concern with wild horses right now
is that there are about 90,000 of them
on our public lands in the West in an
area in which there's only supposed to
be 27,000 horses
[Music]
with such a high population density what
can happen as you start to have pretty
severe ecological degradation especially
in areas where water is a very scarce
resource
unfortunately when there's nothing to
eat or there's no water to drink animals
end up starving or dying of dehydration
which is a cruel way to go and that's
not how we're supposed to manage them
[Music]
in 2016 perk did some research looking
at the wild horse issue and they came up
with some ideas about incentive payments
to help remove some of the wild horses
from the holding pens
[Music]
but they determined was that if the vlm
actually paid people to take the horses
off the range that they could remove
almost all of the horses from the
holding pens based on estimated demands
for wild horses
[Music]
the incentive payment program provides
the wild horses with good homes and it
reduces the expenditures taxpayers are
paying to keep these horses in the
holding pens somebody who really wants a
wild horse
can take this financial incentive use it
hire a professional horse trainer and
give that horse a good life
[Music]
welcome guys glad you're here everybody
can hear me okay and they're extremely
intelligent a lot of people say Mustangs
are very difficult to train I get along
with them pretty well
I've learned a way to communicate with
them effectively
I figured out that instead of me trying
to make that horse a person and treat it
like a person I become another horse I
become the alpha horse in the herd and
they thrive and crave confident
leadership when you can fill that role
for them they just excel we want to coax
out that softness and we want to push
out the bad wild behavior that we don't
like oh yeah good girl you know what
that's a thousand dollar bill right
there and you're gonna read that code so
you got the feel inside which is you we
have thousands of horses in holding long
term and short term that need homes
I just tried to train them show that
these horses have Worth and educate
people and tell them that these are
great horses and I just have a great
passion for him and I like to show what
they're capable of
[Music]
in my opinion the best horse that you
can have or for trail riding in general
animals that for generations have been
naturally selected for that very
environment
[Music]
the exciting thing about the incentive
program and not thousand dollars is
those people that are on the fence it
gives them the cushion to get by maybe
they needed a few more panels or maybe
they just needed their hay so I think
the monetary value has been huge and I
think it's something that BLM will look
forward to continuing in the future the
satisfaction of knowing you had a
completely wild animal and you gentled
it and trained it and now it's a
positive member of societies a pretty
it's a pretty amazing accomplishment
you're not only helping the horse find a
home you're helping your own public land
recover you're helping find the solution
to a huge problem that we all need to
work together to solve
[Applause]